all right hello everyone
it's February 1st 2023
and we're in
cohort three of the paradol textbook
group
meeting number two
we're having our first discussion on
chapter one
so
would anybody like to just give any
opening thoughts or comments
anything that they expected preferred
enjoyed remembered
about chapter one like what was
something they were expecting and got or
didn't or something that stuck with them
about the experience of chapter one
you can raise your hand or just go for
it
how about oh yes please go for it
someone or
Chance favors the prepared mind
my sense was that it gave a kind of
overview but
um
uh it
I I spent my time looking at chapter two
because it kind of gives us broad
overview but you feel the meat is in the
the rest of the book
so I was bogged down and uh
maths of chapter two
awesome yes thank you
and I'll copy your comment in Jonathan
yes rereading taking another look
and just
letting it play out
the first read and then coming back
again and again and seeing more each
time
um and a lot of the formalisms are not
in chapter one so
there is meat slash nutrition elsewhere
but also there's interesting insights
within the chapter and I'm sure it
sparked people to think about
um different things so anyone else feel
free to go for it like just
any sections of chapter one or any
framings that you remembered or you
highlighted or that stuck out to you
soon
Luigi oh thank you
foreign
motivates or excites people about
learning active
um
they situate the question that active
seeks to address as how do living
organisms persist while engaging in
adaptive exchanges with their
environment
pretty interesting
[Music]
um
is that the question that people thought
active inference
was going to seek to address
do they think active
May address another question as well
okay
as always just like feel free to raise
your hand or write something in the chat
or we'll just keep
exploring along
so I've not come across the neat
scruffy's dichotomy so that was a nice
perspective let's look at that
does anybody want to
um
summarize the needs and scruffies
or give like what did they think need
scruffy's means
or what was it doing at this part of the
book
and I I think uh my my take on it
um as a so I'm a physicist originally
I'm so looking at it from sort of
building from the ground up
um you know creating unified theories of
things where everything is explainable
within some framework versus those who
try to look at the details and build
from the details up to to understand the
phenomena that was kind of my my
perspective on this
all right Ollie and then anyone else
yeah well actually I recommend this
um essay each time because I really like
it
um for um in the book Andy Clark and his
critics uh there's a beautiful essay by
Carl Preston mainly beyond the desert
landscape in which he explains in a very
beautiful prose the difference between
uh low road and the high road and it
goes into much further details about the
significance of these two approaches and
the pros and cons of conservich and also
the importance of
looking at the same the same phenomena
uh call it intelligence sentience or
agency or whatever from these two
perspectives and what can we glean from
looking at it from uh those to
perspectives so I highly recommend uh
reading this essay which you can find a
PDF for the for that essay on resources
page as well
thanks
thank you
foreign
neat
unified imperatives
scale-free systems
low road gets scruffy there's a lot of
last miles in the low road because every
generative model
is different
and they're complementary roads
to meet in the middle with octave Kate
or anyone else
um this is still pertaining to the
scruffies and needs I was just it just
occurred to me as I was both reading the
um introduction and now listening to
this how many of us here would be
self-described needs and self-described
scruffies I'm personally a definitely a
need I'm very much gravitating towards
an underlying common explanation for
everything so which draws me to the
active inference as such so I'm just
wondering in the group of us
where would we fall in that
curious awesome
very fun question yeah does anybody want
to
um
dox themselves in terms of being a knee
or a scruffy or some secret third thing
and just share like why that resonates
with them
and how they might see learning active
bolstering how they are
or providing some other
support
blue and then anyone else
so definitely a scruffy
um and uh you know like I mean I strive
towards neat right because I realize
that like order is is
um sometimes preferable I'm drawn to
active inference because I really feel
like it's a kind of a creative lens with
which to view like everything so it's
just another like set of rose-colored
glasses that I put on
um and like I also paint and do other
things and so sometimes like I'll be
staring at a person like I wonder how I
would represent their nose in charcoal
likes it so it just it's like one of
those things it's just a pair of glasses
that I um put on but I do want to also
draw the connection between
um what we were talking about yesterday
on the book stream so I don't know who's
watching that but um we had like you
know they're talking about leadership
styles
and there's like the antagonistic neural
network perspective where there are two
um like opposing not opposing maybe
unifying neural networks one is called
the task positive Network and the other
is the default mode Network
um with the task positive Network being
very like oriented at getting things
done
um it struck me as like a more orderly
thing like maybe in in line with like
the needs and the direct or default mode
Network being more like people-centered
and creativity
um focused and like it's also like the
difference between like right and left
brain I mean we hear all these things
all the time right
um there's like The Logical versus
emotional and so so perhaps like
it's maybe not neat or scruffy but maybe
it's both right I don't know
thanks Ali and then anyone else
um I also think that this distinction
between needs and scruffies uh somehow
relates to uh reductionism versus
emergentism uh which is pretty hot to
date uh nowadays in the philosophy of
science so uh
well of course we know that science for
the most part was uh basically a
reductive Endeavor and most scientists
um by large are reductivists but
nowadays especially from the mid 90s and
the Advent of the complexity theories
and dynamical systems and so on uh
another Viewpoint called emergentism
is actually emerging no pun intended and
uh but there was always a debate between
which one can provide uh the most
insightful discussions uh in in each
particular situations that
nowadays some philosophers uh kind of
take the middle ground between those two
uh such as the contextual emergentism uh
which has been described in this recent
book emergence in context
and I think active inference kind of
maps in my view perfectly to this point
of view of contextual emergentism and
it's the best of Two Worlds in some
sense it's purely reductive
Viewpoint and in another sense uh it's
it can be described as an emergent as
Viewpoint at least the branch of
emergentism called weak emergentism
great a lot of
threads there and fun comments in the
chat so Maria I failed to see how one
can work with details without some
theory behind is it possible with active
just
anyone give a thought
um but I totally agree
implicitly
always and explicitly often we do need
some sort of
combination
and also it kind of maps just like even
a little bit more Loosely like
industrial versus farmers market or
Boutique
and I think in the book
um
they uh basically say like
right before the needs and scruffies
okay
here's the two perspectives
one perspective is that
just the incredible diversity of Bio
biological systems and neural processes
each require a dedicated explanation so
we're going to have a journal or a
theory or an acronym or an undergraduate
major for just serotonergic synapses
that's one option every single phenomena
is going to have its own farmer's market
bespoke scruffy Theory
that would lead to the proliferation of
fields with little hope
for unification
the neat perspective
is recognizing diverse manifestations
but asking whether those
phenomena of broadly perception
cognition and action
from a lens of persistence and
adaptation in life
whether there might be some coherent
explanations
that again recognize the diversity of
manifestations and then help us
understand it
Michael and then Jonathan
foreign
I can't see
Michael or Jonathan
um
go ahead Jonathan I'll follow
um just to say that perhaps this sort of
dichotomy between
um a high road and a low road is kind of
a matter of perspective in the sense
that active inference itself
um you know it's it's it's a description
of certain types of systems but there
are other types of systems out there and
so if one wants to look at a higher
level view then in some sense you know
active inference and the free energy
principle are themselves the low road of
some higher level principle
um higher level physics principle
whatever it is you want
very interesting roads all the way up
slash down
uh Michael
yes in this conversation I may be saying
that I thought whatever was neat and
maybe I'm a scruffy uh the uh I want to
jump back for just a second to what is
the key question instead of um I I was
troubled by that particular phrasing and
I I was like what what would I have
possibly said and I'll put in the chat
but for me the question is how does life
interrogate life
um uh it it there's this stance between
poetry and plumbing and that um there's
a lot of this conversation that is a
plumbing conversation and a part of the
way Consciousness
uh makes sense and speaks is poetry and
um and that that's one of the things
that um that is is the dance here of not
not an either or which is a plumbing way
of describing something but
um uh opposites and paradoxes uh that
are both um
simultaneously considered and that
um that Consciousness supports
um an active inference supports a way of
both
um problem solving and contemplating
mystery both concurrently and that this
is part of the kind of uh
there's something about not just the
problem solving but the the the the the
being related in a way that is not um
agentic if you will that I think is is
missing and and and some of this
thank you and that that really ties in
well with what blue brought up like the
task positive network is like the
getting things done and the default mode
is like the Mind wandering and the
receptivity and there's just an
oscillation between those two modes in
neural systems
Nathan welcome and yes please anything
you want to add
um yeah so I mean you're talking about
plumbing and poetry and you just we're
talking about tpn DM where we're
switching between these two modes of
thinking
um
and before that we're
talking about like higher and lower
levels of you know thinking about this
whole problem so are we making the claim
that like active inference is like are
are we making the claim that this is
like the appropriate layer of
abstraction to look at this problem
because when we usually look at big
problems like this we have to pick a
layer of abstraction where we're not
losing like a lot of detail and
resolution but um by going higher up in
abstraction but obviously we don't want
to get bogged down by the complexity of
adding more detail and resolution
very interesting question
I guess just one very logistical way to
address it is we're reading chapter one
that's giving us an overview of the book
then we're going to have like a month
to talk about the low road to active
inference and the high road to active
inference and that's gonna bring us
to active inference itself so at least
rhetorically
or pedagogically
in terms of how to lay out an argument
and or layout an educational approach it
seems like the authors do believe that
thinking about neats and scruffies
and the resolution
or the the unification of them
not through homogenization but by
recognizing those two perspectives that
that is an important construct
in at the very least understanding and
or learning active
and then
maybe that will bring us to the question
of whether it's also the appropriate
level of abstraction
in application
Ali and then anyone else
uh actually I don't think we can
associate a single level of abstraction
to active inference framework because uh
as far as I understand it active
imprints can equally be applied to
multiple levels of abstractions and it's
somehow uh
non- it's the scale free framework or in
other words where multiple scale
Frameworks so even
if we if we talk about temporal scales
or even spatial scales we can apply it
onto various
various scales and various levels of
abstractions so uh yeah it's not it's a
much more broader framework than we can
associate with some other theories which
specifically are a little limited to a
particular level of abstraction so
that might
we can see some of the examples for
these different levels of abstractions
especially in the second part of the
book
awesome thanks
so
um
let us turn to
some of the questions that people
prepared so does anyone see a question
that they
wrote that they would like to ask and we
can explore
or we'll go with the ones that people
have upvoted
but if anybody has like one that they
wrote or just want to highlight let's go
to it
and also it's awesome like I saw a lot
of people adding comments on the
questions
um
all right
let's just go to the most uploaded one
then
bring the question down into here so
it's just a little more visible
okay on page six it refers to active
inference as a normative framework there
are some evaluative standard against
which behavior can be scored which is
free energy
specifically the minimization of
variational version thereof so just to
plant the seed but we're gonna come back
to it later
the two kinds of free energy that we're
going to be talking a lot about are
variational and expected but we're going
to come back to that but for now let's
just think about free energy
as a unified imperative for perception
cognition and action
variational is in the present
and expected has to do with futures
then it refers to planning to achieve
distal goals in humans
does this definition of normative mean
that octave is agnostic about precisely
what humans goal that might be
one human may wish to save the world
another may wish to rule the world both
are essentially minimizing free energy
I might be mixing up a few Concepts here
but the gift is that active models don't
predict a socially normative course of
action would that be correct to say
all right
what would anybody like to add on
normativity
of active
what does it mean to say that active is
a normative framework
does that refer to social norms or what
kind of normativity is being described
Ali go for it
I guess at the most fundamental level uh
the normativity admits the agent uh to
be persist through time uh so uh one
meaning of normativity can be uh seen
from the most fundamental requirement of
a system or quote-unquote thing to
actually exist or persist through time
but of course we can apply this concept
onto some higher levels of conceptions
such as social normativity and so on but
yeah again it applies to multiple levels
of abstraction
thank you Jonathan
yeah that that sort of requirement for
wanting to persist Through Time feels
like an an evolutionary imperative and
there are other imperatives into in
terms of our sort of homeostatic set
points and comfort and and hunger and
things like that which then lead to
um the thing which has been
evolutionarily
um uh sort of chosen through time so it
feels like the two kind of have a
um there's a balance between the two in
in terms of hierarchies of scales of
time I guess
thank you
thank you Scott for bringing in that
quote
so I I often compare active with linear
regression
because they're both modeling Frameworks
that are quantitative and so sometimes
it helps to be like okay is this
statement true of linear regression
and there's things that are true for
both octave and linear regression those
like are just true of modeling or
quantitative models and then there's
things that are different between active
and linear regression those are like the
features that differentiate octave and
linear regression so we might say that a
linear regression
is normatively using this kind of
imperative function
like to fit the least squares or the L2
Norm
and it's just saying this framework is
going to use this imperative
to draw a straight line through points
and kind of by analogy
act INF is going to use an imperative
turns out it's a free energy functional
that we're going to go into in the
coming chapters
it uses that unified imperative
not to draw a straight line through
points like a linear regression does
but to describe Bayes optimal perception
cognition and action
so it's doing something similar
instead of having like one imperative
for perception and then a different
imperative for action
it's a unified model
of perception cognition and action
that we can use this one imperative
the free energy of a generative model
and use that to guide
the fine-tuning or the learning of that
generative model
to return to the social question as we
move forward
no it is not like uh
an ought
it's not the is odd this is not an
ethical framework
just because there's a normative way to
fit a linear regression doesn't mean
that
it tells you what any given culture
is going to be happy or upset or benefit
from or anything like that
there's probably a lot there's other
ways to say it but just the short answer
is
this is correct
octave is not in the kernel of active
is not describing social normativity in
the sense of like peer pressure or like
what people will look at you weirdly if
you do
okay
next question
living organisms can only maintain their
bodily Integrity by exerting adaptive
control over the action perception Loop
which they frame that adaptive control
as the question that active seeks to
address
do generative models represent and
thereby predict bodily integrity
or do these models predict the causes of
their sensory inputs
and Via minimizing the prediction error
they achieve maintaining their bodily
Integrity without explicitly predicting
bodily integrity
how to best talk about what a generative
model is predicting
great questions what does anyone want to
add
well I think one short answer and then
Ali is that generative models fit
whatever parameters they have
so you could imagine making a generative
model
where there's like a hidden state that
is bodily integrity
and then
there's observations that help reduce
uncertainty about bodily
um integrity
so in that case we'd say yes the
generative model represents bodily
Integrity as a hidden state
and therefore tries to
do inference using that
or do these models predict the causes of
their sensory input and Via minimizing
prediction error they achieve
maintaining their bodily integrity
that's actually like another way to say
something similar
which is that the hidden states are the
latent causes of sensory observations
and so by minimizing the prediction
error
with respect to observations
it is possible to achieve maintenance or
homeostasis of those latent States
even though they are not they are
explicitly predicted or represented but
they're not observed
Ali anyone else
uh well actually an acts of inference uh
all the agents or more technically all
all the particular systems and all the
particles sorry uh do are kind of doing
the this kind of inference making tasks
in order to
self-evidence and actually this task of
self-evidencing is the fundamental uh
task that an agent needs to undertake in
order to uh
keep its homeostasis into action or uh
doing uh that kind of homeostasis
through allostasis because both of those
terms are obviously related one of which
needs a more active
um and more and more active
mediation to to undertake the the
homeostasis test but in any case uh the
the concept of self-evancing exactly
refers to this kind of uh Integrity
maintaining uh
task that any
self any inference making agent needs to
undertake to persist through time so I
think this is the fundamental
requirement of any agents modeled in
active inference framework
awesome thank you
and once we start into the subsequent
chapters and we look at how preference
is used in active inference we'll have
some awesome discussions like
do we expect
homeostatic temperatures or do we prefer
them it's like on one hand I prefer it's
what I like
on the other hand it's what I expect
because I wouldn't be surprised to find
myself there so how does that play out
um ever
yes and you hear me okay
okay so a good good answer also depends
on which level of the hierarchy you are
talking
um so at the lowest of hierarchy there's
sensory
stimuli that's are being predicted and
the more you move up the more abstract
models or predictions are taking place
so higher up the hierarchy I could have
predictions about bodily Integrity
or predictions about my continuing
existence
Etc and then lower down the hierarchy
you could have some physiological
variable that's predicted like
nociception in the case of pain
and then you can have all
awesome
okay was that is that all
yes okay okay yes totally agree
um
often people talk about like nested
models or hierarchical models
multi-scale models and that's one of the
strengths of taking of at least bringing
some neatness into play is like
by using
a level of neatness that lets us
generalize across different cognitive
phenomena like what we might just
conversationally call low level or high
level
it allows those models to be composed in
an integrated way
so
in this textbook there's not going to be
an emphasis on nested modeling it's
going to focus on like the kernel of
active inference which is like the
single agent at the single level
but then there's all of these
elaborations which are active areas of
research and development
um outside of the textbook yes thank you
Yana
could you clarify low and high level
yeah
I think that they uh if I think about
the cortical
hierarchy there's I think six layers
uh
um and and if I read the literature
correctly they talk about
different kind of predictions depending
on which kind of cortical area you are
talking about
and and the active inference models are
built
in a way that's go that's also uh fits
uh the anatomy of the brain so they talk
about computational Anatomy fitting the
active inference models
thank you Jonathan and then John Luigi
um yeah I think that that's right I
think another perspective is is simply
that low level is for instance the the
pure sensory inputs themselves
um we may be making predictions about
you know a site that um something that
will come to our eyes higher level might
be some
um sort of more abstract idea of the
thing that it is outside in the world
that is is giving us the sensory input
and so there's a sort of hierarchy of
um time scales and physical scales
um that we might take in moment to
moment and build up a bigger and bigger
picture
awesome so just to restate that at the
engine Luigi the low level this is just
one spatial metaphor
is that the pure sensory inputs
themselves like the low level is where
the rubber hits the road
and then the higher levels
are abstract or synthesized
representations about what are giving
rise to those sensory data and that is
also called a cause in the statistical
sense
Luigi
than ever
yeah
um I also believe that it really depends
on how your generative model is set up I
mean a high level
can also be a pretty straightforward
sensory uh inference so to say between
one observation and one hidden State and
not something absolutely abstract or at
least that's what I saw like I I agree
that plastically it has been like those
cortical layers or the the lower levels
are the most most
um low level sensory uh inputs so so to
say and the higher levels are the more
abstract ones but I do believe that they
also uh that the distinction might also
not be that strict
all right and then effort
then there's a few more points to make
yeah and this question uh about what is
predicted also uh
um I think it also has to be seen from
this uh instrumentalist and realist
discussion uh is it is it the modeler
that uh is building an active inference
model and tries to infer what the
organism at whatever level is predicting
uh and and that's what I wonder is um
you you also read in the literature A
lot of times that they talk
um with the terms as if it looks as if
the organism is minimizing this or that
or predicting this or that so this s if
language
um
also makes me wonder how how do we know
what an organism is predicting
awesome this instrumentalist and realist
and map territory we're going to return
to a lot
um on I want to bring a few more points
on the nested models and then we'll
return to the questions since
um like nested modeling it's kind of
like
the active kernel is like one Lego brick
with like a bottom and a top part and
then like it is very amenable and as
soon as we have the Legos we want to
stack and put them in lateral and build
them
but the multi-level Lego structure is
predicated on what that one is at least
understanding what it is so
in live stream 28
on um sandved Smith's paper this is just
one example of a nested model with three
layers
where the quote low level is sensory
and then there's a level of attention
and meta awareness so there's not just
one way to do nested models there's many
nested models that one can make but it's
an example of how something that is like
raw and exteroceptive
can be seen as a low level model nested
Within
other models that are quote higher but
again that's just like a that's just
like a a cultural visual graphical
layout there's no reason why it couldn't
be from left to right or top to bottom
or inside to out so it's like it's about
what it is not just the spatial layout
but that's what it is
on the six levels of the brain so here's
from um live stream 43 which was with
Maria
um
yes there are six anatomical layers in
parts of the mammal brain
six layers that are defined like
histologically like the tissues look
different
but
it's really important to remember that
is not the same thing as it's not six
nested Legos
and we're gonna get to this more when we
get to chapter five which is all about
um the neuroscience
but here are those six layers
so this is not six full nested models
like here's three full nested models
that are truly nested whereas the six
histological layers
actually are part of an integrated
inference scheme
it's not six nested models
but a lot of times people think oh
multi-level models hierarchical Bayesian
modeling hierarchical predictive coding
architectures
six layers in the brain six nested
models that's not true
but that's a very common
um
framing
so what is the generative model
predicting whatever it is set up to
predict these are maps not territories
okay I think okay great
there were some some awesome discourse
here
so can someone explain to me
why the inferential problem is
intractable page eight it has to do with
the marginal likelihood P of Y in the
Bayes theorem so does anyone here
who is in this discussion like want to
summarize it
or what their understanding of what is
the tractability issue
and how are we going to approach that
um yes am I the the sort of example I
gave there was that if you see a flash
of light you want to know what's the
probability that it is a particular
thing given that you have you've you've
had some observation of the world
um but in order to do that you need to
sum up
um in this case all of the different
things that could have given rise to
that particular flash of lights and that
in itself is in is intractable so there
are various terms within the
um within the base equation which in
order to do it properly in a complex
world would mean summing over an
infinite number of things that was my my
thought there
great
so
there's a lot of ways to to talk about
this
but you pointed to that that several
pieces are required to go from a stimuli
to inference about a causal state of the
world like whether it was truly a tiger
giving rise to the stimuli or whether
it's something different
you'd want to know a few things you'd
want to know the probability of given
that it's a tiger what is the
probability it would look like that
flash you saw
but then also you want to know
How likely is that flash from other
possible hidden causes
and so that is like the probability of
The Flash given that it's a tiger or
given as a chipmunk given it's all these
other things
and that can be an open-ended
some
so thanks for that great answer it is in
essence an infinite sum of possible
things
and you'd have to know the probability
to be able to say
what you should really think
there's there's there's many notes like
yeah ever you go for it
no
um I also found in the book that they
say for complex models there maybe
many types of hidden states that all
need marginalizing out making the
problem computationally interactable so
I thought you were saying that before
but I also found that the a sentence the
marginal marginalization operation might
require analytically intractable
integrals and I I don't understand what
that means
is it different than the answer you gave
before
it's it's very related so sometimes um
in a discrete
setting
we are talking about sums like sums you
know one two three four five sum over
one two three four five in a continuous
setting
we are talking about integrals
so if something is being summed over a
discrete range
that is analogous to it having an
integral over a continuous range and so
they're both beset with the same
challenges of large
um and interacting spaces
and then just one kind of note because
on a Bayesian and marginalization this
is like actually the margins of a piece
of paper
that's what it's referring to when
there's kind of like Actuarial tables
back when statistics was done on
spreadsheets
so it's like if you have states of the
world and then observations in in a grid
um if each observation mapped onto one
hidden state of the world
then you would just have like only on
the diagonal would you have any numbers
we're going to come back to these topics
but then you can imagine that you might
be interested in marginalizing a given
row
like summing across that row
so saying okay How likely is this across
all columns and that's called
marginalization
so why is it intractable
because it might just be requiring
computational resources that are
unrealistic or implausible
okay I think uh it's there was actually
the the reason the whole reason for a
variational free energy a quantity uh
this this marginal likelihood thing
is that correct
yes it is it is free energy
is going to help bound
our surprise
let's but let's come right to it
so this one kind of goes in multiple
different uh directions
the central imperative is that organisms
maintain their existence High Road avoid
surprising States
how can one explain different self-harms
or perceived self-harms
this is kind of like the social norms
question
in that
um we're not always going to get a neat
answer from a human scale complex nested
system where the generative model hasn't
been stated
this if that makes sense so like given a
generative model
one could describe how driving off a
cliff is the mo that is the generative
models most likely course of action like
if the generative model is I always
drive straight I'm likely to find myself
driving straight
that generative model may drive off a
cliff
but to kind of not mention the
generative model and just say well how
is it possible that surprise is bounded
by driving off cliffs
is not
a full
um
it's not fully making contact with what
the surprise is because surprise is with
respect to a generative model
so whether it's the extremely complex
cases of humans
or whether we're talking about something
different
then surprise and the bounding of
surprise through free energy
is with respect to a generative model
everything is always in respect
to generative model
there's no surprise minimization free
energy minimization outside of a
generative model
so surprise immunization free energy
minimization those
are
qualities of a generative model just
like the um least squares regression the
sum of squares is with respect to a
linear regression model
surprise bounding free energy is with
respect to an active inference
generative model and once the generative
model is specified
then one may find different actions
as avoiding surprising States including
addiction and different states that
people have studied that we're going to
come to
but we need to fill out what generative
model we're talking about before
applying the imperative Jonathan and
then Everett
you know within that generative model
there are also
um the the different desired states that
the organism might want to be in and
those desired States you know they're
they're not normative in the sort of
sociological sense we may have different
desired States and so for some some
people that may be very different from
what another person wants and may lead
to one of these outcomes
thank you and ever
yes it's uh this uh example with the
suicide
it's also related to the high roads
where the imperative is to um
maintain our existence minimizing uh
surprise necessary for survival
um so if if I commit suicide and I would
violate that core imperative and but we
do know that people commit suicide so
how can we explain that so this
framework
um and it also has to do with um if I
predict bodily Integrity
um but for example I uh someone who
experiences chronic pain because that's
the best explanation for my prediction
error that I have
will be an update of the model that says
okay now I'm not predicting any bodily
Integrity anymore but I have threats to
my bodily integrity and with that also
then lead to eventually committing
suicide or just some some thoughts but I
can't make really sense of this
um thanks
okay just in our final minutes to touch
on one or two more all these discussions
people can continue to engage and and
develop ad resources ask more questions
like it doesn't stop here this is like
the tip of the iceberg of us wanting to
develop the state on these questions
because they're things that we're all
asking they're things that other people
are going to be curious about and we can
have
great answers
and complex discourse and multiple
perspectives here
um we're just going to do one more and
then we'll end two minutes before
um the hour
and again these are also things we're
going to return to in future weeks this
is just our first week on chapter one
next week we're gonna do another chapter
one session and we'll come through more
questions the second half of the
questions on chapter one and anything
else that people add and upvote so just
in the last three minutes
can someone explain why exploration and
exploitation are automatically balanced
through policy selection in active
inference page 10. what does it mean to
say both exploration exploitation are
balanced
Jana thank you I will save this chat
uh
in my in my understanding it would be
that you only explore as much as
necessary to exploit
so you want so X
exploration is an effort
somehow and you want to minimize this to
get the maximum of exploitation
that's my understanding approximately
thanks
um one uh very Hands-On
uh
way to explore this question is in model
stream 7.2
from just a few days ago
in the video description of model stream
72 there is
[Music]
um
a notebook that can be run in your
browser without any more tweaking
and it is going to have an agent that
has the choice to do a few different
things they can play either of two
different slot machines one of which is
like better than the other or they can
get a hint
and so
um
to have an imbalanced strategy
would be like to kind of Zone into the
first slot machine you go to and stay
there
to have a overly imbalanced strategy
towards um exploration that might look
like just getting the hint every time or
just kind of moving around really
rapidly in the space but not ever like
latching on to ones that have high
utility
and then a balance strategy
which there's not just one single answer
to this but a balanced strategy in a
given situation is an action policy
selection it's a strategy or tactics
that navigate or manage the tensions of
the requirements between exploration
exploitation and sometimes that's
modeled what's called a multi-armed
bandit where there's like a bunch of
slot machines you want to win the most
money but you don't know how good each
of the slot machines are so you got to
explore a little bit to find out like
how good they are but then you want to
spend most of your time on the best ones
you want to spend time proportional to
how good they are but of course if you
only spend time on what you perceive as
the best things might be changing and so
you might end up not being on the best
machine soon so
thank you everybody for joining
we'll come back next week for the second
discussion on chapter one
and um please
add comments and questions and discourse
in the time till then but thanks
everybody for the awesome discussion
farewell thanks everyone
[Music]